const questions = [
    {
        "numb": 101,
        "question": "Whar does mean the term \"pathogenesis\"?",
        "answer": "the development mechanism",
        "options": [
            "mechanism of death ",
            "the development mechanism",
            "clinical manifestations",
            "complications ",
            "cause of development"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 102,
        "question": "What does mean the term \"tanatogenesis\" ?",
        "answer": "mechanism of death ",
        "options": [
            "complications ",
            "mechanism of death ",
            "the development mechanism",
            "cause of development",
            "clinical manifestations"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 103,
        "question": "What does pathological consequences include?",
        "answer": "Death",
        "options": [
            "self-healing",
            "body malaise",
            "general weakness",
            "transition to latent form",
            "Death"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 104,
        "question": "What may the classification of diseases include?",
        "answer": "?hronic",
        "options": [
            "prodrome",
            "?hronic",
            "initial",
            "latent",
            "terminal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 105,
        "question": "How is called sign of biologic death characterized by not dissappear by pressing to spot?",
        "answer": "Imbibition",
        "options": [
            "Cadaveric drying",
            "Rigor mortis",
            "Cadaveric decomposition",
            "Cadaveric cooling",
            "Imbibition"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 106,
        "question": "How is called sign of biologic death which associated with evaporation of fluid? ",
        "answer": "Cadaveric drying",
        "options": [
            "Cadaveric spots ",
            "Rigor mortis",
            "Cadaveric drying",
            "Cadaveric decomposition",
            "Cadaveric cooling "
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 107,
        "question": "Which cellls most sensitive to hypoxia?",
        "answer": "Neurons",
        "options": [
            "Myocardial cells ",
            "Renal tubular epithelial cells",
            "Hepatocytes",
            "Neurons",
            ""
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 108,
        "question": "If patient has decreased arterio-venous difference of O2, which type of hypoxia more probably is it?",
        "answer": "histogenous hypoxia",
        "options": [
            "circulatory hypoxia",
            "histogenous hypoxia",
            "respiratory hypoxia",
            "exogenous hypoxia",
            "hemic hypoxia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 109,
        "question": "A scientist Dr. Gobind was asked to participate in a research project on myocardial infarction in a rabbit model. Which of the following occurs in ischemic cell injury? ",
        "answer": "Influx of Na+ and Ca++",
        "options": [
            "Influx of Na+ and Ca++",
            "Influx of K+ and Ca++",
            "Efflux of K+ and Na+",
            "Influx of K+ and H 2o",
            "NA"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 110,
        "question": "Among the following, what is the correct sequence of events that occur during necrosis? 1) Cell swelling 2) Karyolysis 3) Karyorrhexis 4) Pyknosis",
        "answer": "1, 4, 3, 2",
        "options": [
            "1,2, 3,4",
            "1, 4, 3, 2",
            "NA",
            "2,3, 4, 1",
            "4, 3, 2, 1"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 111,
        "question": "Which cellular organelle is typically affected in reversible cell injury?",
        "answer": "Mitochondria",
        "options": [
            "Nucleus",
            "Mitochondria",
            "Golgi apparatus",
            "Lysosomes",
            "Endoplasmic reticulum"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 112,
        "question": "A 45-year-old male smoker complains of shortness of breath and cough. Lung biopsy shows hypertrophy and hyperplasia of bronchial epithelial cells. Which cellular adaptation is most likely occurring in this patient's lungs?",
        "answer": "Hypertrophy",
        "options": [
            "Hypertrophy",
            "Metaplasia",
            "Hyperplasia",
            "Atrophy",
            "Dysplasia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 113,
        "question": "Which of the following processes is irreversible?",
        "answer": "Karyorrhexis",
        "options": [
            "Karyorrhexis",
            "NA",
            "Fatty change",
            "Visible vacuoles in cytoplasm",
            "Hydropic swelling"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 114,
        "question": "Which type of necrosis occurs in patients having a history of trauma?",
        "answer": "Fat nonenzymatic necrosis",
        "options": [
            "Fat nonenzymatic necrosis",
            "Gangrene",
            "Liquefactive necrosis",
            "Coagulative necrosis",
            "Fibrinoid necrosis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 115,
        "question": "A 5O-year-old chronic alcoholic presents to the emergency room with 12 hours of severe abdominal pain. The pain radiates to the back and is associated with an urge to vomit. Physical examination discloses exquisite abdominal tenderness. Laboratory studies show elevated serum amylase. Which of following morphologic changes would be expected in the peripancreatic tissue of this patient?",
        "answer": "Fat necrosis ",
        "options": [
            "coagulative necrosis ",
            "Caseous necrosis ",
            "NA",
            "Fat necrosis ",
            "Fibrinoid necrosis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 116,
        "question": "Apoptosis literally means",
        "answer": "Falling off",
        "options": [
            "NA",
            "Die in peace",
            "Falling off",
            "Natural death",
            "Shrink"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 117,
        "question": "Mark the correct statement(s) regarding Caspases: 1) It is an alanine protease in nature 2) Active caspase is a marker for cells undergoing apoptosis. 3) Exists as zymogens and undergo cleavage to get activated 4) Independent of proapoptotic and antiapoptotic proteins 5) Required for embryogenesis ",
        "answer": "Only 2,3,5 is correct ",
        "options": [
            "NA",
            "Only 1,2,3 is correct ",
            "Only 2 is correct  ",
            "Only 1,2.4 is correct ",
            "Only 2,3,5 is correct "
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 118,
        "question": "In which of the following organs fatty changes are not seen?",
        "answer": "Lungs",
        "options": [
            "Kidney",
            "Liver",
            "Lungs",
            "Heart",
            "Muscles"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 119,
        "question": "What is the name of the pathological process which is associated with               accumulation of cholesterol and cholesterol esters with formation of tumorous masses?",
        "answer": "Xantoma",
        "options": [
            "Adenoma",
            "Xantoma",
            "Papilloma",
            "Teratoma",
            "Atheroma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 120,
        "question": "A 68-year-old deceased had changes in the coronary vessels and aorta. Grossly: the walls of the vessels are thickened, hard, with plaques. What pathological process developed in this case?",
        "answer": "Accumulation of cholesterol",
        "options": [
            "Accumulation of cholesterol",
            "Accumulation of amyloid",
            "Accumulation of carbohydrates",
            "Accumulation of proteins",
            "Accumulation of lipids"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 121,
        "question": "What the name of the cells accumulating fat within the intimal layer of aorta and large arteries in atherosclerotic plaques?",
        "answer": "Foam cells",
        "options": [
            "Foam cells",
            "Fibroblasts",
            "Lymphocytes",
            "Epithelial cells",
            "Leukocytes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 122,
        "question": "A 50-year-old patient with chronic renal failure underwent biopsy. When staining with Congo-Red, it was revealed: extracellular, homogeneous, structure less, masses, red color. What type of dystrophy in this case? ",
        "answer": "Amyloidosis",
        "options": [
            "Hemosiderosis",
            "Hemochromatosis",
            "Fatty change",
            "Hyalinosis",
            "Amyloidosis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 123,
        "question": "What do amyloid fibrils represent?",
        "answer": " Insoluble fibrils in the extracellular ",
        "options": [
            " Cellular organelles",
            "Cellular structures that enable movement",
            " Insoluble fibrils in the extracellular ",
            " Soluble proteins in cells",
            "Liquid inclusions in cells"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 124,
        "question": "What the name of substance with fibrillary structure which forms under the pathological conditions?",
        "answer": "Amyloid",
        "options": [
            "Reabsorbtion droplets",
            "Lipids",
            "Calcificates",
            "Russell bodies",
            "Amyloid"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 125,
        "question": "What causes of posthepatic jaundice?",
        "answer": "Obstruction of bile ducts by stones",
        "options": [
            "Hemolytic disease of newborns",
            "Liver cirrhosis ",
            "Heterohemotransfusions ",
            "Obstruction of bile ducts by stones",
            "Hepatitis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 126,
        "question": "Which of the fol lowing are true about Xeroderma pigmentosum : A. Skin manifestations appear within first 2 years of life B. Increased risk of non melanotic skin cancers c. Nucleotide excision repair defect D. Autosomal dominant inheritance ",
        "answer": "A, B, C are true ",
        "options": [
            "NA",
            "B C Only",
            "B, C, D are true",
            "A and Bare true ",
            "A, B, C are true "
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 127,
        "question": "Which pigment derived from hemoglobin found in normal conditions? ",
        "answer": "Bilirubin",
        "options": [
            " Hemomelanin",
            "Bilirubin",
            "Porphyrin",
            "Hemin ",
            "Hematoidin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 128,
        "question": "At 33-year-old patient have white skin color, blond hair, poor vision and severe photophobia. They are highly sensitive to sunlight. What pigment exchange disorder is there in this case?",
        "answer": "Melanin",
        "options": [
            "Hematoidin",
            "Porphyrins",
            "Hemosiderin",
            "Bilirubin",
            "Melanin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 129,
        "question": "What is metastatic calcification?",
        "answer": "deposition of calcium salts in normal tissues",
        "options": [
            "derangement in calcium and phosphate metabolism",
            "deposition of calcium salts in normal tissues",
            "Hypervitaminosis D",
            "Increased bone catabolism",
            "deposition of calcium salts in dead tissues"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 130,
        "question": "Which of the following is true about calcification? Which organ will not have metastatic calcification?",
        "answer": "Psammoma body is formed with dystrophic calcification ",
        "options": [
            "Psammoma body is formed with dystrophic calcification ",
            "Mitochondria is the rarest organelle affected in calcification",
            "It is most commonly seen in the kidneys ",
            "NA",
            "Serum calcium is normal in metastatic calcification "
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 131,
        "question": "Which of the following conditions is characterized by a primary respiratory acidosis?",
        "answer": "Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)",
        "options": [
            "Hypokalemia",
            "Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)",
            "Renal failure",
            "Excessive vomiting",
            "Diabetic ketoacidosis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 132,
        "question": "A 54-year-old male patient in renal failure has missed a round of dialysis and was feeling sick. What is the probable acid-base disorder that we can expect in this patient?",
        "answer": "Metabolic Acidosis",
        "options": [
            "NA",
            "Metabolic Acidosis",
            "Respiratory Acidosis",
            "Metabolic Alkalosis",
            "Respiratory Alkalosis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 133,
        "question": "What is the primary treatment for dehydration?",
        "answer": "Fluid replacement",
        "options": [
            "Fluid replacement",
            "Administering antihistamines",
            "Restricting fluid intake",
            "Administering antidiuretic hormone",
            "Administering diuretics"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 134,
        "question": "Which of the following may cause edema? 1. Elevated vascular hydrostatic pressure 2. Reduced vascular hydrostatic pressure 3. Elevated plasma osmotic pressure 4. Reduced plasma osmotic pressure",
        "answer": "1 and 4",
        "options": [
            "NA",
            "1 and 3",
            "1 and 4",
            "2 and 3",
            "2 and 4"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 135,
        "question": "Macro signs of arterial hyperemia is which one of these?",
        "answer": "increased tissue turgor",
        "options": [
            "increased number of capillaries",
            "fast blood flow",
            "decreased number of capillaries",
            "low local temperature",
            "increased tissue turgor"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 136,
        "question": "A 66-year-old patient suffered from chronic ischemic heart disease died from chronic heart failure accompanied by chronic venous hyperemia of internal organs. At autopsy: the lung tissue is brown, hard, airless. Microscopically: accumulation of hemosiderin and fibrosis of the lung tissue are determined. What term is used for this pathological process in lungs?",
        "answer": "Brown induration",
        "options": [
            "Cirrhosis of lung",
            "Brown induration",
            "Congestive induration",
            "Muscat cirrhosis",
            "Nutmeg lungs"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 137,
        "question": "Indicate what one of following signs Virchow\u2019s triad, as etiology of one of local circulation disorders, includes?",
        "answer": "injured vessel wall",
        "options": [
            "low oxyhemoglobin",
            "fast blood flow",
            "injured vessel wall",
            "hypocoagubility",
            "smoot vessel wall"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 138,
        "question": "Which outcome of thrombus is characteristic by dislodge and transport to other sites?",
        "answer": "Embolization",
        "options": [
            "Suppuration",
            "Embolization",
            "Calcification",
            "Dissolution",
            "Propagation "
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 139,
        "question": "What type of embolism can occur in bone fracture?",
        "answer": "Fat embolism",
        "options": [
            "Thromboembolism",
            "Fat embolism",
            "Gas embolism",
            "Microbial embolism",
            "Amniotic fluid embolism"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 140,
        "question": "Which type of embolism can cause a syndrome similar to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), with rapid development of severe hypoxemia and neurologic changes?\n\n",
        "answer": " Fat embolism\n",
        "options": [
            " Fat embolism\n",
            "Amniotic fluid embolism\n",
            " Air embolism\n",
            " Foreign body embolism.\n",
            "Septic embolism\n"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 141,
        "question": "Which feature characterizes ischemia as a local circulation disorder?",
        "answer": "pallor",
        "options": [
            "increased blood flow",
            "edema",
            "pallor",
            "cyanosis",
            "redness"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 142,
        "question": "During ischemia will be pale color of tissue due to which one of following?",
        "answer": "decreased  number of functional capillaries",
        "options": [
            "reduced hemoglobignal level",
            "decreased  number of functional capillaries",
            "increased number of functional capillaries",
            "increased hemoglobin level",
            "increased oxyhemoglobin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 143,
        "question": "Which term used for hemorrhage from urinary system? ",
        "answer": "Haematuria",
        "options": [
            "Haematemesis",
            "Epistaxis",
            "Haemoptoe",
            "Metrorrhagia",
            "Haematuria"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 144,
        "question": "A 63-year-old patient who suffered from myocardial infarction and died from  acute heart failure. During autopsy was revealed: defect of the wall of left ventricle and blood in the pericardial cavity. Which term is used for this type of hemorrhage?",
        "answer": "Hemopericardium ",
        "options": [
            "Hemothorax",
            "Hemarthrosis",
            "Hemoperitoneum",
            "Hematomesis",
            "Hemopericardium "
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 145,
        "question": "Shock due to cardiac tamponade is an example of ",
        "answer": "Obstructive shock",
        "options": [
            "Distributive shock",
            "Hypovolemic shock",
            "Endocrine shock",
            "NA",
            "Obstructive shock"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 146,
        "question": "A patient 30 years old after the injection developed edema, redness and itching at the injection site, a severe decrease of blood pressure (40/20 mm Hg). Pathanatomical examination revealed: fluid blood in the vessels, accumulation of blood in microcirculatory vessels, disseminated intravascular coagulation, \u201cshock kidney\u201d, \u201cshock lung\u201d. Which type of shock occurs in this case? ",
        "answer": "Anaphylactic ",
        "options": [
            "Traumatic ",
            "Cardiogenic",
            "Anaphylactic ",
            "Hypovolemic",
            "Septic"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 147,
        "question": "In which type of shock we can see decreased of the peripheral vascular resistance? ",
        "answer": "Hypovolemic shock",
        "options": [
            "Cardiogenic shock",
            "Hypovolemic shock",
            "Obstructive shock",
            "Distributive shock",
            "NA"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 148,
        "question": "An immunocompromised patient presents in the ER with fever, dyspnea and altered sensorium. His heart rate is 124 bpm, BP is 90/66 mm of Hg, and his central venous pressure (CVP) is low. What is the patient suffering from?",
        "answer": "Septic shock",
        "options": [
            "NA",
            "Cardiogenic shock",
            "Septic shock",
            "Hypovolemic shock",
            "Obstructive shock"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 149,
        "question": "Which of the following best describes the primary initiating event in the pathophysiology of DIC?",
        "answer": "Release of tissue factor into circulation",
        "options": [
            "Endothelial injury resulting in exposure of subendothelial collagen",
            "Release of tissue factor into circulation",
            "Dissemination of malignant cells into the bloodstream",
            "Impaired fibrinolysis leading to fibrin deposition",
            "Activation of the intrinsic pathway of coagulation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 150,
        "question": "A 30-year-old pregnant female presents to the obstetrics ward with complaints of vaginal bleeding, abdominal pain, and decreased fetal movement. Laboratory tests show thrombocytopenia, elevated fibrin degradation products (FDPs), and prolonged clotting times. Obstetric ultrasound reveals intrauterine fetal demise. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
        "answer": "Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)",
        "options": [
            "HELLP syndrome",
            "Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura",
            "Acute fatty liver of pregnancy",
            "Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)",
            "Antiphospholipid syndrome"
        ]
    }
];